Guide to the Jacob Milgrom Papers
Department of Special Collections
Jacob Milgrom papers,
ca. 1945- 1994
M1002
Milgrom, Jacob, 1923-
3.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Professional correspondence, clippings, student papers, some early class work by Milgrom, notes, reprints, ephemera. His book collection is particularly strong in Bible and rabbinic literature.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased with book collection, 1994.
Biography / Administrative History
Rabbi, author, and University of California at Berkeley Professor Emeritus Biblical Studies Jacob Milgrom was born in Brooklyn, New York on February 1, 1923. He studied at Brooklyn College before earning advanced degrees from the Jewish Theological Seminary. In 1948 he married Jo Milgrom (nee Berman), a biblical scholar in her own right; they have four children. Jacob Milgrom's research interests include Leviticus, the Dead Sea Scrolls, and Tannaitic literature; over the course of his distinguished career he published five books and more than two hundred articles. He was named a fellow of the Guggenheim Foundation, a fellow of the Institute for Advanced Studies in Jerusalem, and a senior fellow of the Algright Institute of Archaelogical Research. Rabbi Milgrom retired in 1992. He and his wife now reside in Jerusalem, Israel.
Scope and Content of Collection
Clippings, photocopies, professional correspondence, student papers, writings by others, some early course work by Milgrom, notes, reprints, and ephemera.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Book collecting; Judaica and Hebraica Collections
Collection Contents
- Bibliographies, Series 1; 1 folder
  - (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printed, typed, and handwritten bibliographies from various sources.
- Book Fragments, Series 2; 1 folder
  - (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pages 241-253 from Anmerkungen zu Kapitel IV, undated.
- Calendars, Series 3; 1 folder
  - (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Two calendars: Keren Hayesod United Israel Appeal, 1957/58 and 1959/60.
- Conference Materials, Series 4; 1 folder
  - (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Agendas and other materials from various conferences, 1970s, 1980s, and undated.
- Correspondence, Series 5; 1 folder
  - (Box 1, Folder 5)
    17 notes, letters, and memos dating from 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s.
- Course Materials, Series 6; 19 folders
  - Exams, Subseries 6.1; 1 folder
    - Course materials: Exams (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Three exam blue books written by Rabbi Milgrom. History I and History II dated May 17, 1945; Med[ieval] Hebrew Literature undated, ca. 1945.
  - Lecture Notes, Subseries 6.2; 9 folders
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Lectures notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Typed notes from history course taken by Rabbi Milgrom, 1945.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Handwritten notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, 1943 and undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Handwritten notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Typed notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Handwritten notes from course on Ugaritic taken by Rabbi Milgrom, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Typed notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, 1942 and undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Typed and handwritten notes from courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Handwritten notes from lecture attended by Rabbi Milgrom and Jo Milgrom, "Sabbath Eve Service in Babylonia," undated.
  - Lecture Outlines, Subseries 6.3; 4 folders
    - Course materials: Lecture outlines (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Typed outlines of courses taken by Rabbi Milgrom, dated 1943-44.
    - Course materials: Lecture outlines (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Typed outline of lecture series "Redemption of Israel and Return to Zion," World Jewish Bible Society, Jerusalem, ca. 1960.
    - Course materials: Lecture outlines (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Typed syllabus for religious school confirmation class, undated.
    - Course materials: Lecture outlines (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Typed course proposal: "Introduction to the Thought of A.J. Heschel," by Gary L. Austern. Undated.
  - Readings, Subseries 6.4; 5 folders
    - Course materials: Readings (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Readings to accompany various lectures.
    - Course materials: Readings (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Course materials: Readings (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Course materials: Readings (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Course materials: Readings (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 7; 1 folder
  - Diary (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Jerusalem Diary" kept by Rabbi Milgrom during tour of Israel. Undated.
- Directories, 8; 1 folder
  - Directories (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Two directories. The Jewish Education Yellow Pages (Coalition for the Advancement of Jewish Education), 1993, and The Rabbinical Assembly of America, 1961.
- Educational Games, 9; 2 folders
  - Educational games (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Set of small cards for bible quiz game printed with quotations. Undated.
  - Educational games (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Bible quiz game. Undated.
- Indices, 10; 1 folder
  - Indices (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Index to topics in Buber's Tales, prepared by Rabbi Elliot B. Gertel. Undated.
- Judaica and Religious Observance, 11; 10 folders
  - Commentaries, 11.1; 3 folders
    - Judaica/Religous observance (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Studies in the Weekly Sidrah, by Nechama Leibowitz. English and Hebrew. 1950s.
    - Judaica/Religous observance (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Book. Masekhet avodah zarah min talmud bavli im perushe ve-tosafot masoret ha-shas. Vilna: defus ve-hotsaat ha-almanah veha-ahim rom, 662 [1901]. 126 p. Condition poor.
    - Judaica/Religous observance (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Two booklets. Mishnayot, by Eliezer Levi. New York: hotsaat Feldheim, undated. 14 p. Stamped "Property of Camp Ramah" on cover. Mishah meforeshet: masekhet brakhot, me'et Eliezer Levi. Tel Aviv: hotsaat Sinai: 721 [1961 or 62]. Stamped "Camp Ramah Conover, Wisconsin" on t.p.
  - Ketubot, 11.2; 2 folders
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Ketubot (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Ten copies of three different blank ketubot [certifcates of marriage]. English and Hebrew, undated.
    - Judaica and religious observance (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Tenoyim [marriage contract]. Blank form in Hebrew, printed by Ferlag fun Yehuda Katsenelenboygen, 66 Kanal Strit, Nyu York. Undated.
  - Liturgies, 11.3; 5 folders
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Liturgies (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Two booklets. Mahzor: a prayerbook for the high holy days. Berkeley, CA: Kehilla Community Synagogue, 1985.Photocopy: Afternoon readings for Yom Kippur. Undated.
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Liturgies (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Looseleaf booklet. Cover reads: A Contemporary High Holiday Service, ed. by Rabbi Sidney Greenberg and S. Allan Sugarman. Bridgeport, CT: Prayer Book Press of Media Judaica, 1970. Some pages missing, out of order.
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Liturgies (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Two booklets. Mahzor for Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur: A prayer book for the days of awe. Berkeley, CA: The Aquarian Minyan, undated. 62 p.Untitled prayer book for Days of Awe. Beyt Chesed, compiled by Carol Delton, Patricia Warner-Cohn and Max Weinryb. Undated. 23 p.
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Liturgies (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Four booklets. A Prayer for divine aid (to be recited during the war), by Louis Ginzberg. Jewish Theological Seminary of America, undated.Sidur katan, by Zeev Folk. Jerusalem: Skorpyo 88, 753 [1992 or 93]. Inscribed "le-Yaakov ule-Yokheved be-birkat aliyah la-arets vela-torah, Berkli, 25 Shevat 754 [1993 or 94]. Yizkor Book of Remembrance. Richmond, VA: Temple Bethel, Dr. Jacob Milgrom, Rabbi. Undated, 24 p.Megilat Ester The Book of Esther, translated and revised by Rabbi Simon Glazer. New York: Ktav Publishing House, undated. Genizah Service, by Arie Becker. Photocopy, undated, 6 p.
    - Judaica/Religous observance: Sermon outline (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Sermon outline material on Mordecai M. Kaplan supplied by Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, Inc. Undated. 2 p. and cover letter, photocopied.
- Maps, 12; 1 folder
  - Maps (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Small collection of tourist maps from Israel, Europe, and the US.
- Milgrom Family, 13; 2 folders
  - Jeremy Milgrom, 13.1; 2 folder
    - Milgrom Family: Jeremy Milgrom (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Handmade class memory book presented at end of school year to Jeremy Milgrom [son of Jacob and Jo Milgrom] upon leaving school in Jerusalem. 1992.
    - Milgrom Family: Jo Milgrom (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Four letters addressed to Jo Milgrom [wife of Jacob Milgrom]. 1963 and 1980s.
- Offprints, 14; 7 folders
  - Offprints:1930s and 1940s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Offprints from 1930s and 1940s.
  - Offprints:1950s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Offprints from 1950s.
  - Offprints:1960s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Offprints from 1960s.
  - Offprints:1960s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Offprints:1970s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Offprints from 1970s.
  - Offprints:1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Offprints from 1980s.
  - Offprints:1990s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Offprints from 1990s.
- Postcards, 16; 1 folder
  - Postcards (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Four small sets of tourist postcards from Japan and Egypt, unused.
- Prints, 17; 1 folder
  - Prints (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Six color prints. Arthur Szyk, "Rosh Hashana," "Succot," "Simchath Torah," "Chanukah," Purim," "Passover," and "Hillel." c. Arthur Rothmann Fine Arts, Inc., N.Y.C. Undated.
- Public Programs, 18; 1 folder
  - Postcards (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Four programs and event announcements.
- Published Materials, 19; 17 folders
  - Clippings, 19.1; 2 folder
    - Published materials: clippings (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Articles cut or torn from various publications.
    - Published materials: clippings (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 19.2; 1 folder
    - Published materials: newsletters (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Two newsletter issues: CLAL News and Perspectives, Nov. 1987 v.3 no.1.Unidentified "Newsletter # 1" having to do with archaeology in Israel. 6 p.; p. 1-2 missing. 1962-63.
  - Periodicals, 19.3; 1 folder
    - Periodical (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Single issue, ha-Doar. New York: Hebrew Publishing Company, v XLIII, n. 23 (1908). April 5, 1963.
  - Photocopies, 19.4; 12 folders
    - Published materials: periodical (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Single issue of Faith and Form: Journal of the Interfaith Forum on Religion Art and Architecture. Vol XXIII Winter 1989-90.
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Photocopies from journals and monographs relating to Rabbi Milgrom's areas of interest.
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Published materials: photocopies (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Slides, 20; 1 folder
  - Slides (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Five Kodachrome slides. Dated Oct., 1976.
- Unpublished Writings by Others, 21; 1 linear ft.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Development of the Amidah, by Louis Finkelstein in J.T.S.A. J.Q.R. Vol XVI, No. 1. Typewritten, annotated in ink. Undated.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 2)
    The Firstling of Unclean Animals, by Gershon Brin, Tel Aviv University, Israel. Typewritten, annoted in ink, undated.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 3)
    The Conservative Movement and the Synagogue, by Jack J. Cohen. Word processed [photocopy?], undated.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Six Sermon Lectures. The Vision of a Layman: "A Kingdom of Priests, a Holy People" by Rabbi Ralph Simon, Rodfei Zedek, Chicago IL. The Architect of Conservative Judaism: Solomon Schechter: As I knew him, by Rabbi Herman H. Rubenovitz, Rabbi Emeritus Temple Mishkan Teflia [sic], Newton, Mass.Teacher, Scholar, Martyr, by Rabbi Morris Adler, Shaarey Zedek, Detroit, MichiganThe Courage to Stand for Something: The Jew from Italy, Builder of American Judaism" and The Bold Adventurer: "A Pioneer for an Ancient Faith in a New Land," by Rabbi Saul I. Teplitz, Congregation Sons of Israel, Woodmere, Long Island.The Soul of a People: biographical outline of Hillel Bavli (1893-1961). Suggested Material for a Neilah Sermon for Seminary Year of Dedication, compiled by Louis M. Levitsky. All marked "(Not for Publication)," dated 1963-1964.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Book Review. Kathe Kollwitz: Life in Art. Submitted to Jo Milgrom from Student Mary J. Murphy. January 2, 1985.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Notebook: Avodah Zarah. Yerahmiel Hazan. Handwritten, 1961 or 1962.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 7)
    "Notes on Moses Maimonides taken by Rabbi Leo Geiger, 1948."
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Two essays: Freud on Moses and Monotheism, by Leo Strauss. Typewritten, undated.A Religion Like All Other Religions, by Harold M. Schulweis. Inscribed "For Jack and Jo with warmest regards Harold." Undated
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Three essays. Non-Jews in a Jewish Polity: Subject or Sovereign? by David Novak. Undated.Jewish Unity: A Call for Cooperation and Mutual Respect. JWNA-religious Jewish Lay Leaders Dialogue convened by Am Jew Committee [sic]. Sept. 4 1986.From The Hymn of the Universe by Pierre Teilhard de Chardin. Undated.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Six essays. The Kyrenia Ship. Brief account of recovered artifacts, undated.The Holocaust and Theology, by Bernard M. Loomer. Two copies, undated.Israel: People and Land in Jewish Theology, by Ben Zion Bergman, University of Judaism. Undated.Christian Theology and the Holocaust, by A. Durwood Foster. Undated.Christian Beliefs and Anti-Semitism by: Charles Y. Glock and Rodney Stark: Comments on a Survey, by Shaun J. Sullivan, O.F.M. Paper given at Graduate Theological Union-University of Judaism colloquium May 6-8, 1975. People and Land in Christan Theology, by Wilhalm Wuellner, Professor of New Testament, Pacific School of Religion.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Various writings on Martin Buber on the occasion of his 80th birthday.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Two essays: Ritual Needlework: A Contribution of Jewish Women, by Joseph B. Horowitz. Undated.The Holocaust At Second Hand, by Chana Bloch. Undated.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Chapters from dissertation of Roy Gane. Dated 11/13/91.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Chapters from dissertation of Roy Gane. 1991.
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Unpublished writings by others (Box 9, Folder 8)